<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of religion agreed vpon by the archbishops, and bishops, and the rest of the clergie of Ireland, in the conuocation holden at Dublin in the yeare of our Lord God 1615. for the auoyding of diuersities of opinions: and the establishing of concent touching true religion.</title>
            <title>Articles. 1615</title>
            <author>Church of Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843134</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 991:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of religion agreed vpon by the archbishops, and bishops, and the rest of the clergie of Ireland, in the conuocation holden at Dublin in the yeare of our Lord God 1615. for the auoyding of diuersities of opinions: and the establishing of concent touching true religion.</title>
                  <title>Articles. 1615</title>
                  <author>Church of Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Y[oung] for T. Downes, and are to be sold at the great north doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF RELIGION, AGREED VPON BY The Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and the reſt of the Clergie of Ireland, in the Conuocation HOLDEN AT DVBLIN IN The yeare of our Lord God 1615. for the auoyding of Diuerſities of Opinions: And the eſtabliſhing of Concent touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true RELIGION.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R.Y.</hi> for <hi>T. Downes,</hi> and are to be ſold at the great North doore of <hi>Paules.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Headpiece: rectangular decoration; in the center, grain sheaf flanked by two lions enclosed in circle surrounded by the motto "cor unum via una". Not found in McKerrow.</figDesc>
                  <q>COR VNVM VIA VNA</q>
               </figure> Articles of Religion agreed vpon by the Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and the reſt of the Clergie of Ireland in the Conuocation holden at Dublin in the yeare of our Lord God 1615. for the auoyding of Diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Opinions, and the eſtabliſhing of Conſent touching true RELIGION.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the holy Scripture, and the three Creeds.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>1</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ground of our Religion, and the Rule of Faith, and all ſauing Truth is the Word of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>2</label> By the name of holy Scripture we vnderſtand all the Canonicall Bookes of the Old and New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:3"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Of the Old Teſtament.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 5. <hi>Bookes of Moſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ioſua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iudges.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ruth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The first and ſecond of Samuel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The firſt and ſecond of Kings.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The firſt and ſecond of Chronicles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eſra.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nehemiah.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Esther.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iob.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalmes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prouerbs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſong of Salomon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ieremiah his propheſie and Lamentation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ezechiel</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> 12. <hi>leſſe Prophets.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Of the New Teſtament.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Goſpels according to</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Matthew.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Marke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Luke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Epiſtle of S. Paul to the Romanes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Corinthians</hi> 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galathians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philippians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Coloſsians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Timothie</hi> 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Titus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philemon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Epiſtle of S. Iames.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saint Peter</hi> 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saint Iude.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Reuelation of S. Iohn.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:3"/>
               <p>All which wee acknowledge to bee giuen by the inſpiration of God, and in that regard to be of moſt certaine credit and higheſt authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>3</label> The other Bookes commonly called <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall,</hi> did not proceed from ſuch inſpiration; and therefore are not of ſufficient authoritie to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh any point of Doctrine, but the Church doth reade them as Bookes containing many worthy things for example of life and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of manners.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Such are theſe following.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The third Book of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fourth Booke of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Booke of Tobias.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The booke of Iudith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Additions to the book of Eſther.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The booke of Wiſedome</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The booke of Ieſus the Sonne of Sirach, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eccleſiaſticus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baruch with the Epiſtle of Ieremiah.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſong of the three Children.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Suſanna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bell and the Dragon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Prayer of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The firſt booke of Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſecond booke of Macchabees.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>4</label> The Scriptures ought to be tranſlated out of the originall tongues into all languages for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe of all men: neither is any perſon to be diſcouraged from reading the Bible in ſuch a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,
<pb facs="tcp:7845:4"/>as he doth vnderſtand, but ſeriouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to reade the ſame with great humilitie and reuerence, as a ſpeciall meanes to bring him to the true knowledge of God, and of his own duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>5</label> Although there bee ſome hard things in the Scripture (eſpecially ſuch as haue proper rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the times in which they were firſt vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and propheſies of things which were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to bee fulfilled) yet all things neceſſary to be known vnto euerlaſting ſaluation are cleerely deliuered therein: and nothing of that kinde is ſpoken vnder dark myſteries in one place, which is not in other places ſpoken more familiarly and plainly, to the capacitie both of learned and vnlearned.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>6</label> The holy Scriptures containe all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſaluation, and are able to inſtruct ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently in all points of faith that wee are bound to beleeue, and all good duties that we are bound to practiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>7</label> All and euery the Articles contained in the <hi>Nicen Creede,</hi> the <hi>Creede</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and that which is commonly called the <hi>Apostles Creede,</hi> ought firmely to be receiued and beleeued; for they may be proued by moſt certaine warrant of holy Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:4"/>
               <head>Of faith in the holy Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>8</label> THere is but one liuing and true God euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, without body, parts, or paſſions, of infinite power, wiſedome, and goodnes, the maker and preſeruer of all things, both viſible, and inuiſible. And in vnity of this Godhead, there bee three perſons of one and the ſame ſubſtance, power, and eternity: the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>9</label> The eſſence of the Father doth not beget the eſſence of the Son; but the perſon of the Father begetteth the perſon of the Sonne, by communicating his whole eſſence to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon begotten from eternity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>10</label> The holy Ghoſt proceeding from the Father and the Son, is of one ſubſtance, maieſtie and glory, with the Father and the Sonne, very and eternall God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Gods eternall decree, and Predeſtination.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>11</label> GOD from all eternity, did by his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable counſell ordaine whatſoeuer in time ſhould come to paſſe: yet ſo, as thereby no violence is offered to the wils of the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures, and neither the liberty nor the
<pb facs="tcp:7845:5"/>contingency of the ſecond cauſes is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but eſtabliſhed rather.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>12</label> By the ſame eternall counſell God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated ſome vnto life, and reprobated ſome vnto death: of both which there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine number, known only to God, which can neither be increaſed nor diminiſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>13</label> Predeſtination to life, is the euerlaſting pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, wherby, before the foundations of the world were layed, he hath conſtantly decreed in his ſecret counfell to deliuer from curſe and damnation, thoſe whom he hath choſen in Chriſt out of mankinde, and to bring them by Chriſt vnto euerlaſting ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as veſſels made to honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>14</label> The cauſe mouing God to predeſtinate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life, is not the foreſeeing of faith, or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, or good works, or of any thing which is in the perſon predeſtinated, but onely the good pleaſure of God himſelfe. For all things being ordained for the manifeſtation of his glory, and his glory being to appeare, both in the workes of his Mercy and of his Iuſtice, it ſeemed good to his heauenly Wiſedome, to chooſe out a certain number, towards whom he would extend his vndeſerued mercy, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the reſt to be ſpectacles of his iuſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>15</label> Such as are predeſtinated vnto life, be called according vnto Gods purpoſe (his ſpirit work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in due ſeaſon) and through grace they obey the calling, they be iuſtified freely, they
<pb facs="tcp:7845:5"/>be made ſons of God by adoption, they be made like the Image of his only begotten Son Ieſus Chriſt, they walke religiouſly in good workes, and at length by Gods mercy they attaine to euerlaſting felicity. But ſuch as are not predeſtinated to ſaluation, ſhall finally be condemned for their ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>16</label> The godly conſideration of Predeſtination and our election in Chriſt, is full of ſweete, pleaſant, and vnſpeakeable comfort to godly perſons, and ſuch as feele in themſelues the working of the ſpirit of Chriſt, mortifying the works of the fleſh, and their earthly mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and drawing vp their minds to high and heauenly things: as well becauſe it doth greatly confirme and eſtabliſh their faith of eternall ſaluation to bee enioyed through Chriſt, as becauſe it doth feruently kindle their loue towards God: and on the contrary ſide, for curious and carnall perſons, lacking the ſpirit of Chriſt, to haue continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies the ſentence of Gods predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, is very dangerous.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>17</label> We muſt receiue Gods promiſes in ſuch wiſe as they be generally ſet forth vnto vs in holy Scripture: and in our doings, that will of God is to be followed, which wee haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declared vnto vs in the Word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:6"/>
               <head>Of the creation and gouernment of all things.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>18</label> IN the beginning of time, when no creature had any being, God by his word alone, in the ſpace of ſixe dayes, created all things, and afterwards by his prouidence doth continue, propagate, and order them according to his owne will.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>19</label> The principall creatures, are Angels &amp; Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>20</label> Of Angels, ſome continued in that holy ſtate wherein they were created, and are by Gods grace for euer eſtabliſhed therein: others fell from the ſame, and are reſerued in chaines of darkneſſe vnto the iudgement of the great day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>21</label> Man being at the beginning created accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Image of God (which conſiſted eſpecially in the Wiſedome of his minde, and the true Holineſſe of his free-will) had the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of the Law ingrafted in his heart: whereby God did promiſe vnto him euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, vpon condition that he performed entire and perfect obedience vnto his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, according to that meaſure of ſtrength wherewith he was endued in his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and threatned death vnto him, if he did not performe the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:6"/>
               <head>Of the fall of man, originall ſinne, and the ſtate of man before iuſtification.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>22</label> BY one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death went ouer all men, for as much as all haue ſinned.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>23</label> Originall ſinne ſtandeth not in the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Adam (as the Pelagians dreame) but is the fault and corruption of the nature of euery perſon, that naturally is ingendred and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated from Adam: whereby it commeth to paſſe, that man is depriued of originall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and by nature is bent vnto ſinne. And therefore in euery perſon borne into the world, it deſerueth Gods wrath and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>24</label> This corruption of nature doth remaine euen in thoſe that are regenerated, whereby the fleſh alwayes luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and cannot bee made ſubiect to the Law of God. And how ſoeuer for Chriſts ſake there bee no condemnation to ſuch as are regenerate, and doe beleeue: yet doth the Apoſtle acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that in it ſelfe this concupiſcence hath the nature of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>25</label> The condition of man after the fall of Adam is ſuch, that he cannot turne, and prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his owne naturall ſtrength and good
<pb facs="tcp:7845:7"/>workes, to Faith, and calling vpon God. Wherefore wee haue no power to doe good works, pleaſing &amp; acceptable vnto God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the grace of God preuenting vs, that we may haue a good will, and working with vs when we haue that good will.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>26</label> Workes done before the grace of Chriſt, and the inſpiration of his ſpirit, are not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto God, for as much as they ſpring not of faith in Ieſus Chriſt, neither do they make men meet to receiue grace, or (as the Schoole-Authors ſay) deſerue grace of congruity: yea rather, for that they are not done in ſuch ſort as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, we doubt not but they are ſinfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>27</label> All ſinnes are not equall, but ſome far more heynous than others, yet the very leaſt is of its owne nature mortall, and without Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, maketh the offendor lyable vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>28</label> God is not the Author of ſinne: howbeit he doth not onely permit, but alſo by his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence gouerne &amp; order the ſame, guiding it in ſuch ſort by his infinite wiſedome, as it turneth to the manifeſtation of his owne glory, and to the good of his Elect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:7"/>
               <head>Of Chriſt, the mediator of the ſecond Couenant.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>29</label> THe Son, which is the Word of the Father, begotten from euerlaſting of the Father, the true and eternall God, of one ſubſtance with the Father, tooke mans nature in the womb of the bleſſed Virgin, of her ſubſtance: ſo that two whole and perfect natures, that is to ſay, the Godhead and Manhood, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably ioyned in one perſon, making one Chriſt very God and very man.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>30</label> Chriſt in the truth of our nature, was made like vnto vs in all things, ſinne only excepted, from which he was clearly voide, both in his life &amp; in his nature. He came as a Lambe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, to take away the ſins of the world, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe once made, and ſin (as S. Iohn ſaith) was not in him. He fulfilled the Law for vs perfectly: For our ſakes he endured moſt grieuous torments immediatly in his ſoule, and moſt painfull ſufferings in his body. He was crucified, and died to reconcile his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto vs, and to be a ſacrifice not only for originall guilt, but alſo for all our actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. He was buried and deſcended into hell, and the third day roſe from the dead, and tooke againe his body, with fleſh, bones, and all things appertaining to the perfection of mans nature: wherewith he aſcended into
<pb facs="tcp:7845:8"/>Heauen, and there ſitteth at the right hand of his Father, vntill he returne to iudge all men at the laſt day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the communicating of the grace of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>31</label> THey are to be condemned, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay, that euery man ſhall bee ſaued by the law or ſect which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, ſo that he be diligent to frame his life according to that law, and the light of nature. For holy Scripture doth ſet out vnto vs onely the name of Ieſus Chriſt whereby men muſt be ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>32</label> None can come vnto Chriſt, vnleſſe it bee giuen vnto him, and vnleſſe the Father draw him. And all men are not ſo drawne by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they may come vnto the Sonne; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there ſuch a ſufficient meaſure of grace vouchſafed vnto euery man, whereby hee is enabled to come vnto euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>33</label> All Gods elect are in their time inſeparably vnited vnto Chriſt, by the effectuall and vitall influence of the holy Ghoſt, deriued from him, as from the head, vnto euery true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his myſticall body. And being thus made one with Chriſt, they are truely regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and made partakers of him and all his benefits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:8"/>
               <head>Of Iustification and Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>34</label> WE are accounted righteous before God, only for the merit of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, applyed by faith: and not for our owne workes or merits. And this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which we ſo receiue of Gods mercy and Chriſts merits, imbraced by faith, is taken, accepted, and allowed of God, for our perfect and full iuſtification.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>35</label> Although this iuſtification be free vnto vs, yet it commeth not ſo freely vnto vs, that there is no ranſome paid therfore at all. God ſhewed his great mercy in deliuering vs from our former captiuity, without requiring of any ranſome to be paid, or amends to be made on our parts: which thing by vs had beene vnpoſſible to be done. And wheras all the world was not able of themſelues to pay any part towards their ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, it pleaſed our heauenly Father, of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy, without any deſert of ours, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for vs the moſt precious merits of his own Sonne, whereby our ranſome might be fully paid, the Law fulfilled, &amp; his iuſtice fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. So that Chriſt is now the righteouſneſſe of all them that truly beleeue in him. He for them paid their ranſome by his death. He for them fulfilled the Law in his life. That now in him, and by him, euery true Chriſtian man may be called a fulfiller of the Law: for as much as
<pb facs="tcp:7845:9"/>that which our infirmity was not able to effect, Chriſts iuſtice hath performed. And thus the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; mercy of God doe embrace each other: the grace of God not ſhutting out the iuſtice of God in the matter of our iuſtification; but only ſhutting out the iuſtice of man (that is to ſay, the iuſtice of our own works) from being any cauſe of deſeruing our iuſtification.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>36</label> When we ſay that we are iuſtified by Faith only, we doe not meane, that the ſaid iuſtifying Faith is alone in man, without true Repentance, Hope, Charity, and the Feare of God (for ſuch a faith is dead, and cannot iuſtifie) neither do we meane, that this our act to beleeue in Chriſt, or this our faith in Chriſt, which is within vs, doth of it ſelfe iuſtifie vs, or deſerue our iuſtification vnto vs, (for that were to account our ſelues to bee iuſtified by the vertue or dignity of ſome thing that is within our ſelues:) but the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and meaning thereof is, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we heare Gods Word, and beleeue it, although we haue Faith, Hope, Charity, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the Feare of God within vs, and adde neuer ſo many good workes thereunto: yet we muſt renounce the merit of all our ſaid vertues, of Faith, Hope, Charity, and all our other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and good deedes, which wee either haue done, ſhall do, or can do, as things that be far too weake and vnperfect, and vnſufficient to deſerue remiſsion of our ſins, and our iuſtification: and therefore we muſt truſt only in Gods mercy, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7845:9"/>the merits of his moſt dearly beloued Sonne, our only Redeemer, Sauiour, and Iuſtifier, Ieſus Chriſt. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe faith doth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend vs to Chriſt for our iuſtification, &amp; that by faith, giuen vs of God, we embrace the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Gods mercy, and the remiſsion of our ſins, (which thing none other of our vertues or workes properly doth:) therefore the Scripture vſeth to ſay, that <hi>Faith without workes;</hi> and the ancient Fathers of the Church to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that <hi>onely Faith</hi> doth iuſtifie vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>37</label> By iuſtifying Faith wee vnderſtand not onely the common beliefe of the Articles of Chriſtian Religion, and a perſwaſion of the truth of Gods Word in generall; but alſo a particular applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the gracious promiſes of the Goſpell, to the comfort of our owne ſoules; whereby we lay hold on Chriſt, with all his benefits, hauing an earneſt truſt and confidence in God, that he will be mercifull vnto vs for his onely Sonnes ſake. So that a true beleeuer may be certaine, by the aſſurance of faith, of the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, and of his euerlaſting ſaluation by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>38</label> A true liuely iuſtifying Faith, and the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Spirit of God, is not extinguiſhed, nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away in the regenerate, either finally or totally.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:10"/>
               <head>Of ſanctification and good workes.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>39</label> ALl that are iuſtified, are likewiſe ſanctified: their faith being alwaies accompanied with true Repentance and good Workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>40</label> Repentance is a gift of God, whereby a godly ſorrow is wrought in the heart of the faithfull, for offending God, their mercifull Father, by their former tranſgreſſions, together with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reſolution for the time to come to cleaue vnto God, and to leade a new life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>41</label> Albeit that good workes, which are the fruits of faith, and follow after iuſtification, cannot make ſatisfaction for our ſinnes, and endure the ſeuerity of Gods iudgement: yet are they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and accepted of him in Chriſt, and doe ſpring from a true and liuely Faith, which by them is to be diſcerned, as a tree by the fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>42</label> The workes which God would haue his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to walke in, are ſuch as he hath commanded in his holy Scripture, and not ſuch works as men haue deuiſed out of their own braine, of a blind zeale, and deuotion, without the warrant of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>43</label> The regenerate cannot fulfill the Law of God perfectly in this life. For in many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all: and if we ſay, we haue no ſinne, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:10"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>44</label> Not euery heynous ſinne willingly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after Baptiſme, is ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt and vnpardonable. And therefore to ſuch as fall into ſin after Baptiſme, place for repentance is not to be denied.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>45</label> Voluntary workes beſides, ouer and aboue Gods commandements, which they call works of Supererogation, cannot be taught without arrogancy &amp; impiety. For by them men doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that they doe not onely render vnto God as much as they are bound to doe, but that they doe more for his ſake, man of bounden duety is required.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſeruice of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>46</label> OVr duety towards God is to beleeue in him, to feare him, and to loue him with all our heart, with all our minde, and with all our ſoule, and with all our ſtrength to worſhip him, and to giue him thankes, to put our whole truſt in him, to call vpon him, to honour his holy Name and his Word, and to ſerue him truly the daies of our life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>47</label> In all our neceſſities we ought to haue recourſe vnto God by prayer: aſſuring our ſelues, that whatſoeuer we aske of the Father in the name of his Sonne (our onely mediator and interceſſor) Chriſt Ieſus, and according to his will, he will vndoubtedly grant it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:11"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>48</label> We ought to prepare our hearts before we pray, and vnderſtand the things that we aske when we pray: that both our hearts and voices may together ſound in the eares of Gods Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>49</label> When Almighty God ſmiteth vs with affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or ſome great calamity hangeth ouer vs, or anie other waightie cauſe ſo requireth; it is our dutie to humble our ſelues in faſting, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile our ſinnes with a ſorrowfull heart, and to addict our ſelues to earneſt prayer, that it might pleaſe God to turne his wrath from vs, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vs with ſuch graces as we greatly ſtand in need of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>50</label> Faſting, is a withholding of meat, drinke, and all naturall food, with other outward delights, from the body, for the determined time of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. As for thoſe abſtinences, which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by publike order of our State, for eating of fiſh and forbearing of fleſh at certaine times and daies appointed, they are no waies meant to be religious faſts, nor intended for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of any ſuperſtition in the choice of meates; but are grounded meerly vpon poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke conſiderations, for prouiſion of things tending to the better preſeruation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>51</label> We muſt not faſt with this perſwaſion of mind, that our faſting can bring vs to heauen, or aſcribe holineſſe to the outward work wrought. For God alloweth not our faſt for the work ſake
<pb facs="tcp:7845:11"/>(which of it ſelfe is a thing meerly indifferent) but chiefly reſpecteth the heart, how it is affected therein. It is therfore requiſit, that firſt, before all things we cleanſe our hearts from ſin, and then direct our faſt to ſuch ends as God will allow to be good: that the fleſh may therby be chaſtiſed, the ſpirit may be more feruent in prayer, &amp; that our faſting may be a teſtimonie of our humble ſubmiſſion to Gods Maieſtie, when we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſins vnto him, and are inwardly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with ſorrowfulneſſe of heart, bewailing the ſame in the affliction of our bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>52</label> All worſhip deuiſed by mans phantaſie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides or contrary to the Scriptures (as wandring on Pilgrimages, ſetting vp of Candles, Stations, and Iubilies, Phariſaicall ſects, and fained Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, praying vpon Beades, and ſuch like ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition) hath not onely no promiſe of reward in Scripture, but contrariwiſe threatnings and maledictions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>53</label> All manner of expreſſing God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, in an outward forme, is vtterly vnlawfull. As alſo all other Images deuiſed or made by man to the vſe of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>54</label> All religious worſhip ought to bee giuen to God alone: from whom all goodneſſe, health, and grace ought to be both asked and looked for, as from the very author and giuer of the ſame, and from none other.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>55</label> The name of God is to be vſed with all reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:7845:12"/>and holy reſpect: and therefore all vaine and raſh ſwearing is vtterly to bee condemned. Yet notwithſtanding vpon lawfull occaſions, an oath may bee giuen, and taken, according to the Word of God, <hi>iustice, iudgement, and truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>56</label> The firſt day of the weeke, which is the <hi>Lords day,</hi> is wholly to bee dedicated to the ſeruice of God: and therefore we are bound therein to reſt from our common and daily buſineſſe; and to beſtow that leiſure vpon holy exerciſes, both publicke and priuate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ciuill Magiſtrate.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>57</label> THe Kings Maieſtie vnder God hath the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and chiefe power, within his Realmes and Dominions, ouer all manner perſons, of what eſtate, eyther Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill, ſoeuer they bee; ſo as no other forraine power hath or ought to haue any ſuperiority ouer them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>58</label> Wee doe profeſſe that the ſupreame gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all eſtates within the ſaid Realmes and Dominions, in all cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Temporall, doth of right appertaine to the kings highneſſe. Neither do we giue vnto him hereby the adminiſtration of the Word &amp; Sacraments, or the power of the Keyes: but that prerogatiue only, which we ſee to haue beene alwaies giuen
<pb facs="tcp:7845:12"/>vnto all godly Princes in holy Scripture by God himſelfe; that is, that hee ſhould containe all eſtates and degrees committed to his charge by God, whether they be Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill, within their duety, and reſtraine the ſtubborne and euill doers with the power of the Ciuill ſword.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>59</label> The Pope neither of himſelfe, nor by any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church or See of Rome, or by any other meanes with any other, hath any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or authority to depoſe the King, or diſpoſe any of his Kingdomes or Dominions, or to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe any other Prince to inuade or annoy him, or his Countries, or to diſcharge any of his ſubiects of their allegeance and obedience to his Maieſtie, or to giue licence or leaue to any of them to beare armes, raiſe tumult, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Royall perſon, ſtate, or gouernment, or to any of his ſubiects within his Maieſties Dominions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>60</label> That Princes, which be excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, may be depoſed or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by their ſubiects, or any other whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, is impious doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>61</label> The lawes of the Realme may puniſh Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men with death, for heynous and grieuous offences.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>62</label> It is lawfull for Chriſtian men, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Magiſtrate, to beare armes, and to ſerue in iuſt wars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:13"/>
               <head>Of our duty towards our Neighbours.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>63</label> OVr duety towards our neighbours, is to loue them as our ſelues, and to doe to all men as we would they ſhould doe to vs: to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; obey our Superiors; to preſerue the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of mens perſons, as alſo their chaſtity, goods, and good names; to beare no malice nor hatred in our hearts; to keep our bodies in temperance, ſoberneſſe, &amp; chaſtity; to be true and iuſt in all our doings; not to couet other mens goods, but labour truely to get our owne liuing, and to doe our duety in that eſtate of life vnto which it pleaſeth God to call vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>64</label> For the preſeruation of the chaſtity of mens perſons, wedlocke is commanded vnto all men that ſtand in need thereof. Neither is there any prohibition by the Word of God, but that the Miniſters of the Church may enter into the ſtate of Matrimony: they being no where comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Gods Law, either to vow the eſtate of ſingle life, or to abſtaine from marriage. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is lawfull alſo for them, as well as for all other Chriſtian men, to marry at their owne diſcretion, as they ſhall iudge the ſame to ſerue better to godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>65</label> The riches and goods of Chriſtians are not common, as touching the right, title, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame; as certaine Anabaptiſts falſly affirme. Notwithſtanding euery man ought of ſuch things as hee poſſeſſeth, liberally to giue almes to the poore, according to his ability.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:13"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>66</label> Faith giuen, is to be kept, euen with Hereticks and Infidels.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>67</label> The Popiſh doctrine of Equiuocation &amp; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Reſeruation, is moſt vngodly, and tendeth plainly to the ſubuerſion of all humane ſociety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Church, and outward Miniſtry of the Goſpell.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>68</label> THere is but one Catholike Church (out of which there is no ſaluation) containing the vniuerſall company of all the Saints that euer were, are, or ſhall be, gathered together in one body, vnder one head Chriſt Ieſus: part whereof is already in Heauen <hi>triumphant,</hi> part as yet <hi>mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> here vpon earth. And becauſe this Church conſiſteth of all thoſe, and thoſe alone, which are elected by God vnto ſaluation, &amp; regenerated by the power of his ſpirit, the number of whom is knowne only vnto God himſelfe; therefore it is called the <hi>Catholike</hi> or vniuerſall, and the <hi>Inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>69</label> But particular &amp; viſible Churches, (conſiſting of thoſe who make profeſſion of the faith of Chriſt, &amp; liue vnder the outward means of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) be many in number: wherein the more or leſſe ſincerely according to Chriſts inſtitution, the Word of God is taught, the Sacraments are adminiſtred, and the authority of the Keyes is vſed; the more or leſſe pure are ſuch Churches to be accounted.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:14"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>70</label> Although in the viſible Church the euill be euer mingled with the good, and ſometimes the euill haue chiefe authority in the miniſtration of the Word &amp; Sacraments: yet for as much as they doe not the ſame in their owne name, but in Chriſts, and miniſter by his commiſſion and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; we may vſe their miniſtery both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Word, and in receiuing the Sacraments. Neither is the effect of Chriſts ordinance taken away by their wickednes: nor the grace of Gods gifts diminiſhed from ſuch, as by faith, &amp; rightly do receiue the Sacraments miniſtred vnto them; which are effectuall, becauſe of Chriſts inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and promiſe, although they be miniſtred by euill men. Neuertheleſſe it appertaineth to the diſcipline of the Church, that inquiry be made of euill Miniſters, and that they be accuſed by thoſe that haue knowledge of their offences, and finally being found guilty, by iuſt iudgement be depoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>71</label> It is not lawfull for any man to take vpon him the office of publike preaching or miniſtring the Sacraments in the Church, vnleſſe hee bee firſt lawfully called, &amp; ſent to execute the ſame. And thoſe we ought to iudge lawfully called and ſent, which be choſen and called to this worke by men, who haue publike authority giuen them in the Church, to call and ſend Miniſters into the Lords Vineyard.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>72</label> To haue publike prayer in the Church, or to adminiſter the Sacraments in a tongue not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb facs="tcp:7845:14"/>of the people, is a thing plainly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, and the cuſtome of the Primitiue Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>73</label> That perſon, which by publike denunciation of the Church, is rightly cut off from the vnity of the Church, and excommunicate, ought to be taken of the whole multitude of the faithfull, as a Heathen and Publican, vntill by Repentance hee be openly reconciled and receiued into the Church, by the iudgement of ſuch as haue authority in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>74</label> God hath giuen power to his Miniſters, not ſimply to forgiue ſinnes, (which prerogatiue he hath reſerued onely to himſelfe) but in his name to declare and pronounce vnto ſuch as truely repent and vnfainedly beleeue his holy Goſpell, the abſolution and forgiueneſſe of ſins. Neither is it Gods pleaſure, that his people ſhould be tyed to make a particular confeſſion of all their knowne ſinnes vnto any mortall man: howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any perſon grieued in his conſcience, vpon any ſpeciall cauſe, may well reſort vnto any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and learned Miniſter, to receiue aduice and comfort at his hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the authority of the Church, generall Councels, and Biſhop of Rome.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>75</label> IT is not lawfull for the Church, to ordain any thing that is contrary to Gods Word: neither
<pb facs="tcp:7845:15"/>may it ſo expound one place of Scripture, that it be repugnant to another. Wherefore although the Church bee a witneſſe, and a keeper of holy Writ: yet as it ought not to decree any thing againſt the ſame, ſo beſides the ſame, ought it not enforce any thing to be beleeued vpon neceſſitie of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>76</label> Generall Councels may not be gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without the commandement and will of Princes: and when they be gathered together (for as much as they be an aſſembly of men not alwaies gouerned with the Spirit and Word of God) they may erre, and ſometimes haue erred, euen in things pertaining to the rule of piety. Wherfore things ordained by them, as neceſſary to ſaluation, haue neither ſtrength nor authority, vnleſſe it may be ſhewed that they be taken out of holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>77</label> Euery particular Church hath authority to inſtitute, to change, and cleane to put away ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and other Eccleſiaſticall rites, as they be ſuperfluous, or be abuſed; and to conſtitute other, making more to ſeemlineſſe, to order, or edification.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>78</label> As the Churches of <hi>Ieruſalem, Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioch</hi> haue erred: ſo alſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath erred, not onely in thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern matter of practice and point of ceremonies, but alſo in matters of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>79</label> The power which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> now challengeth, to be the Supreme head of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall
<pb facs="tcp:7845:15"/>Church of Chriſt, &amp; to be aboue all Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kings and Princes, is an vſurped power, contrary to the Scriptures and Word of God, and contrary to the example of the Primitiue Church: and therefore is for moſt iuſt cauſes taken away, and aboliſhed within the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Realmes and Dominions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>80</label> The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo farre from being the Supreme head of the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt, that his workes and doctrine do plainly diſcouer him to bee <hi>that man of ſinne,</hi> foretold in the holy Scriptures, <hi>whom the Lord ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and aboliſh with the brightneſſe of his comming.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſtate of the Old and New Teſtament.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>81</label> IN the Old Teſtament the Commandements of the Law were more largely, and the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chriſt more ſparingly and darkly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; ſhadowed with a multitude of types and figures, and ſo much the more generally and obſcurely deliuered, as the manifeſting of them was further off.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>82</label> The Old Teſtament is not contrary to the New. For both in the Old and New Teſtament euerlaſting life is offered to mankind by Chriſt, who is the onely Mediatour betweene God and man, being both God and man. Wherefore they
<pb facs="tcp:7845:16"/>are not to bee heard, which faigne that the old Fathers did looke onely for tranſitory promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For they looked for all benefits of God the Father through the merits of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, as we now doe: onely they beleeued in Chriſt which ſhould come, we in Chriſt already come.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>83</label> The New Teſtament is full of grace and truth, bringing ioyfull tidings vnto mankinde, that whatſoeuer formerly was promiſed of Chriſt, is now accompliſhed: and ſo in ſtead of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent types and ceremonies, exhibiteth the things themſelues, with a large and cleare declaration of all the benefits of the Goſpell. Neither is the miniſtery thereof reſtrained any longer to one circumciſed Nation, but is indifferently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto all people, whether they be Iewes or Gentiles. So that there is now no Nation which can truely complaine, that they be ſhut forth from the communion of Saints, and the liberties of the people of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>84</label> Although the Law giuen from God by Moſes, as touching ceremonies and rites bee aboliſhed, and the Ciuill precepts thereof be not of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to be receiued in any Common-wealth: yet notwithſtanding, no Chriſtian man whatſoeuer is freed from the obedience of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are called Morall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:16"/>
               <head>Of the Sacraments of the New Teſtament.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>85</label> THe Sacraments ordained by Chriſt, be not onely badges or tokens of Chriſtian mens profeſſion: but rather certaine ſure witneſſes, and effectuall or powerfull ſignes of grace and Gods good will towards vs, by which hee doth worke inuiſibly in vs, and not onely quicken, but alſo ſtrengthen and confirme our faith in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>86</label> There be two Sacraments ordained of Chriſt our Lord in the Goſpell, that is to ſay, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>87</label> Thoſe fiue, which by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are called Sacraments, to wit, <hi>Confirmation, Penance, Orders, Matrimony,</hi> and <hi>Extreame Vnction,</hi> are not to be accounted Sacraments of the Goſpell: being ſuch, as haue partly growne from corrupt imitation of the Apoſtles, partly are ſtates of life allowed in the Scriptures, but yet haue not like nature of Sacraments with <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> for that they haue not any viſible ſigne or ceremonie ordained of God, together with a promiſe of ſauing grace annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>88</label> The Sacraments were not ordained of Chriſt to be gazed vpon, or to be carried about; but that we ſhould duely vſe them. And in ſuch onely as worthily receiue the ſame, they haue a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome effect and operation; but they that receiue
<pb facs="tcp:7845:17"/>them vnworthily, therby draw iudgement vpon themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>89</label> BAptiſme is not only an outward ſigne of our profeſſion, and a note of difference, whereby Chriſtians are diſcerned from ſuch as are no Chriſtians; but much more a Sacrament of our admiſſion into the Church, ſealing vnto vs our new birth (and conſequently our Iuſtification, Adoption, and Sanctification) by the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we haue with Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>90</label> The Baptiſme of Infants is to bee retained in the Church, as agreeable to the Word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>91</label> In the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme, Oile, Salt, Spittle,</hi> and ſuperſtitious <hi>hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the Water,</hi> are for iuſt cauſes aboliſhed: and without them the Sacrament is fully and perfectly adminiſtred, to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, agreeable to the inſtitution of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>92</label> THe Lords Supper, is not onely a ſigne of the mutuall loue, which Chriſtians ought to beare one towards another, but much more a Sacrament of our preſeruation in the Church,
<pb facs="tcp:7845:17"/>ſealing vnto vs our ſpirituall nouriſhment and continuall growth in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>93</label> The change of the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine, into the ſubſtance of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, commonly called <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> cannot bee proued by holy Writ; but is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to plaine teſtimonies of the Scripture, ouerthroweth the nature of a Sacrament, and hath giuen occaſion to moſt groſſe Idolatrie, and manifold ſuperſtitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>94</label> In the outward part of the holy Communion, the Body and Bloud of Chriſt is in a moſt liuely manner <hi>repreſented;</hi> being no otherwiſe preſent with the viſible elements, than things ſignified and ſealed are preſent with the ſignes and ſeales, that is to ſay, ſymbolically and relatiuely. But in the inward and ſpirituall part, the ſame Bodie and Bloud is really and ſubſtantially <hi>preſented</hi> vnto all thoſe, who haue grace to receiue the Sonne of God, euen to all thoſe that beleeue in his Name. And vnto ſuch as in this manner doe worthily and with Faith repaire vnto the Lords Table, the Bodie and Bloud of Chriſt is not only ſignified and offered, but alſo truely exhibited and communicated.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>95</label> The Bodie of Chriſt is giuen, taken, and eaten in the Lords Supper, only after an heauenly and ſpirituall manner; and the meane whereby the Body of Chriſt is thus receiued &amp; eaten, is Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>96</label> The wicked, and ſuch as want a liuely faith, although they doe carnally and viſibly (as Saint
<pb facs="tcp:7845:18"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) preſſe with their teeth the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt: yet in no wiſe are they made partakers of Chriſt; but rather to their condemnation, do eate and drinke the ſigne or Sacrament of ſo great a thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>97</label> Both the parts of the Lords Sacrament, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts inſtitution, &amp; the practice of the ancient Church, ought to bee miniſtred vnto all Gods people; and it is plaine ſacriledge to rob them of the myſticall cup, for whom Chriſt hath ſhed his moſt precious bloud.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>98</label> The Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> was not by Chriſts ordinance reſerued, carried about, lifted vp, or worſhipped.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>99</label> The ſacrifice of the Maſſe, wherein the Prieſt is ſaid to offer vp Chriſt for obtaining the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of paine or guilt, for the quick and the dead, is neither agreeable to Chriſts ordinance, nor grounded vpon doctrine Apoſtolike: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe moſt vngodly, &amp; moſt iniurious to that all-ſufficient ſacrifice of our Sauiour Chriſt, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red once for euer vpon the Croſſe, which is the onely propitiation and ſatisfaction for all our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>100</label> Priuate Maſſe, that is, the receiuing of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> by the Prieſt alone, without a competent number of communicants, is contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7845:18"/>
               <head>Of the ſtate of the ſoules of men, after they be departed out of this life: together with the generall Reſurrection, and the laſt Iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>101</label> AFter this life is ended, the ſoules of Gods children be preſently receiued into Heauen, there to enioy vnſpeakeable comforts; the ſoules of the wicked are caſt into Hell, there to endure endleſſe torments.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>102</label> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Limbus Patrum, Limbus Puerorum, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, Prayer for the dead, Pardons, Adoration of Images and Reliques,</hi> and alſo <hi>Inuocation of Saints,</hi> is vainly inuented without all warrant of holy Scripture, yea and is contrary to the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>103</label> At the end of this world, the Lord Ieſus ſhall come in the clouds with the glory of his Father: at which time, by the almighty power of God, the liuing ſhall be changed, and the dead ſhall be raiſed; and all ſhall appeare both in body and ſoule before his iudgement ſeate, to receiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which they haue done in their bodies, whether good or euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>104</label> When the laſt iudgement is finiſhed, Chriſt ſhall deliuer vp the Kingdome to his Father, and God ſhall be all in all.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:19"/>
            <head>The Decree of the Synod.</head>
            <p>IF any Miniſter, of what degree or quality ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee be, ſhall publikely teach any doctrine contrary to theſe Articles agreed vpon; If after due admonition he doe not conforme himſelfe, and ceaſe to diſturbe the peace of the Church; let him be ſilenced, and depriued of all ſpirituall promotions he doth enioy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7845:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
